Inventory of the Cole Papers 1786-1938
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Cole Papers, 1786-1939.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 C67
3,031 items.
Accounts, minutes, and correspondence of Henry Denison Cole, lifelong resident of Williamsburg, Virginia and other members of his family.
Cole family
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1939.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry Denison Cole (1856-1938) was the son of Robert F. Cole. Henry D. Cole operated a bookshop on Duke of Gloucester Street, served as postmaster, 1884-1889, treasurer of Bruton Parish Church, secretary of the Alumni of the College of William and Mary, judge of elections, member of the Democratic Committee, the school board, and the Board of Trustees of Eastern State Hospital.
Scope and Content Information
Included are minutes of the Wise Light Infantry Co. of Williamsburg, 1881-1882; the College of William and Mary Alumni Association, 1906-1917; papers concerning the College of William and Mary including letters, 1873, from Benjamin S. Ewell; the Williamsburg Free School Trustees, 1870-1907; and the Democratic Committee of Williamsburg.
Also accounts of the state school funds, 1894-1911; the city school funds, 1906-1911, 1919-1924; Bruton Parish Church 1897-1938; and of Robert F. Cole (father of Henry D. Cole), 1843-1856. Also lists of registered voters in Williamsburg, 1889-1896, 1902-1925, and papers relating to property in Williamsburg and the restoration of Bruton Parish Church, 1905-1906.
The collection also includes stereoptican slides and letters from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series.
Organization
This collection was organized into fourteen Series: 1. Papers of Williamsburg City Council, 2. Papers of Williamsburg Post Office, 3. Miscellaneous Letters, 4. Business Papers of H. D. Cole, 5. Papers of the Cole Family, 6. Papers relating to William and Mary College, 7. Wise Infantry Minute Book, etc., 8. Printed Material and Stereoptican Slides, 9. William and Mary Alumni Association, 10. Post Card and Shop Account Book, 11. Papers Relating to Schools, 12. Bruton Parish Records, 13. Williamsburg Democratic Records, and 14. Artifacts.
Index Terms
Persons:
Roberts, William Thomas.; Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1853-1935.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Rockefeller, Abby Greene Aldrich.; Ewell, Benjamin Stoddert, 1810-1894.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
Subjects:
Williamsburg (Va.). City Council.; Williamsburg (Va.). Post Office.; Bruton Parish Church (Williamsburg, Va.); College of William and Mary--Alumni.; Virginia. Constitutional Convention (1901-1902); Virginia. Militia. Wise Light Infantry.; Democratic Party (Williamsburg, Va.); College of William and Mary--History--20th century.; African Americans--Politics and suffrage--Virginia.; Voting--Virginia--History.; Photography, Stereoscopic.; Schools--Virginia--Williamsburg.; Virginia--Militia--19th century.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--20th century.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--19th century.
Component List
  Series 1: Papers of Williamsburg City Council
- Papers of the Williamsburg City Council, 1889-1899. (Box 1)
  Papers of the Williamsburg City Council, including manuscript draft of the first ordinance regulating automobile traffic, contract for city gas lighting system, duties of city scavenger, pro and con papers regarding bond issue for city water works and sewage disposal and doctors bills for smallpox vaccinations.
  Series 2: Papers of Williamsburg Post Office
- Papers of the Williamsburg Post Office, 1884-1889. (Box-folder 2:1)
  Papers of the post office while Cole served as postmaster.
  Series 3: Miscellaneous Letters
- Miscellaneous Letters, 1888-1934. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Letter from E. W. Blodgett, 9 Oct[ober] 1899., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Blodgett's balloon ascent and public reaction to Dreyfus case.
  - Letter concerning Lynchburg, Virginia, 16 April 1911., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Growth and development around Lynchburg, Virginia.
  - Letters: political and personal, 1888-1936. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Letter concerning C. H. Fine, 1911. (Box-folder 2:2)
  Series 4: Business Papers of H. D. Cole
- Business papers of Henry D. Cole, 1894-1934.
  - Business papers of Henry D. Cole, 1894-1934. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Includes rent and sale contracts for Williamsburg property. Sale for standing lumber, tax returns, fire insurance policies, four certificates from Virginia governors appointing him to the board of trustees of Eastern State Hospital.
  - Additional Henry D. Cole business papers, 1895-1916. (Box 8)
    - Rent collections volume, 1901-1909.
    - Cole's shop volume, 1895-1916. (Box 8)
      Wood and periodical accounts of Cole's shop.
    - Notes, memos and clippings used to prepare post cards and souvenir booklets, 120 items. (Box 8)
  Series 5: Papers of the Cole Family
- Papers of the Cole Family, 1816-1910. (Box 3)
  - Cole Property Papers, 1843-1910. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Papers concerning the property of H. D. Cole, his father Robert F. Cole, his grandfather Jesse Cole and bills of the latter two.
  - Papers of Robert F. Cole, 1849-1856. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Papers of Robert F. Cole. Account books of Robert F. Cole showing accounts against Williamsburg residents.
  - Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 3:3)
    Includes an 1816 letter.
  Series 6: Papers relating to William and Mary College
- Papers relating to William and Mary College, 1847-1901. (Box 4)
  - Letters from Benjamin S. Ewell, 1873., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Legal papers with William and Mary seal signed by Robert Saunders, 1847. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Receipt to Gustavus Lobby for philosophy course signed by Silas Totten, 1851., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - W. T. Roberts Letter, 20 November 1901., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Letter from Roberts who was rector of Bruton Parish Church criticizing the college, president [Lyon G.] Tyler and the vice-president of the Board of Visitors as a "moral leper."
  - Lyon G. Tyler reply to "moral leper letter", 1901. (Box 7)
    Reply of William and Mary president Lyon G. Tyler to November open letter by W. T. Roberts, rector of Bruton Parish Church.
  Series 7: Wise Infantry Minute Book, etc.
- Wise Infantry Minute Book; City-Colonial Williamsburg Agreement; and Yorktown Newspaper Clippings, 1881-1928. (Box 4)
  - Minute Book of the Wise Light Infantry of Williamsburg, Virginia, 1881-1882., 1 bound volume. (Box-folder 4:2)
  - City-Colonial Williamsburg Agreement, 1928., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:2)
    Printed copy of an agreement between the City of Williamsburg and the Williamsburg Holding Company, now Colonial Williamsburg
  - Yorktown Centennial Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 4:2)
    Primarily of Yorktown Centennial Celebration, including 18 October 1881 edition of Army and Navy Register listing events, personages, military units and their officers.
  Series 8: Printed Material and Stereoptican Slides
- Printed Material and Stereoptican Slides, 1861-1911. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Assorted Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Hickory Neck Academy Program, May 1883. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Jamestown Celebration Account, 1 item. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Account of burning of Williamsburg Courthouse, 6 April 1911., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - North Carolina Coupon Bond, 1861., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Stereoptican slides, 125 slides. (Box-folder 4:3)
  Series 9: William and Mary Alumni Association
- William and Mary Alumni Association, ca. 1880-1914. (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1880-1890. (Box 5)
    Contains social, political, historical events and clippings on the October 1888 reopening of the College as well as other items of interest about William and Mary.
  - Bank Book, 1901-1907. (Box 5)
    Bank account book of Henry D. Cole in which pages 68-71 are devoted to William and Mary Alumni Association Executive Committee.
  - Account Book, 1906-1917. (Box 5)
    Newspaper and magazine account book of Henry D. Cole in which pages 250-257 are minutes of meetings of Alumni Association Executive Committee. Volume includes account and memorandum book of Richneck Farm.
  Series 10: Post Card and Shop Account Book
- Post card and shop account book, 1923-1935. (Box 5)
  Series 11: Papers Relating to Schools
- Papers relating to schools, 1870-1924. (Box 6)
  - Bound Volume of Minutes, 1870-1907. (Box 6)
    Minutes of meetings of Trustees of the Williamsburg Free School. The volume also contains miscellaneous loose papers pertaining to the school.
  - School funds volume, 1911-1920. (Box 6)
    Bound volume of accounts of school accounts and funds, both state and local.
  - State school funds volume, 1894-1911. (Box 5)
    Bound volume of accounts of state school funds.
  - City school funds volume, 1906-1911. (Box 6)
    Bound volume of accounts of city school funds.
  - City school funds volume, 1919-1924. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous school board papers
    Includes letters to the school board.
  Series 12: Bruton Parish Records
- Bruton Parish Records, 1897-1930. (Box 7 and 10)
  - Contributions volume, 1930. (Box 7)
    Contributions to Bruton Parish Church.
  - Financial papers of Bruton Parish Church, 1897-1938. (Box 7)
  - Financial and business papers of Bruton Parish Church, 1924-1936. (Box 10)
  Series 13: Williamsburg Democratic Records
- Williamsburg Democratic Records, 1889-1925. (Box 9)
  - Democratic Minute Book, 1889-1896. (Box 9)
    Bound volume of minutes of the Democratic Committee in Williamsburg, registered voters in the city (white and colored [sic]lists). In the back of the volume there is a collection of ballots of the period.
  - Registered voters, 1902-1925., 3 bound volumes (Box 9)
    Lists of registered voters in the city.
  - Presidential campaign minutes, 1900-1904. (Box 9)
    Minutes having to do with Presidential campaigns.
  Series 14: Artifacts
- Artifacts
  Cole family cup and saucer. 18th century Whielden agatewear.